A Guide to the Carl Schurz Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #8376
Carl Schurz Collection 1869-1893
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
8376
33 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Deposit, 1966 Sep 10
Container List
- Manuscript
  - " Abraham Lincoln", 1891; AMsS, 3 p.
    [Title page and introductory note to essay.]
- Letters
  - Carl Schurz to George William Curtis, 1869 Apr 16; ALS, 2 p.
    [Might become a war correspondent in the imminent war between Prussia and France; feels that his familiarity and connections with Germany would make him an able correspondent; believes he will be allowed to accompany Prussian army during the campaign; willing to write exclusively for
    Harper's
    if given the most acceptable terms; has sent similar letters to other prominent papers.]
  - Carl Schurz to George William Curtis, 1871 Aug 14; ALS, 2 p.
    [Discusses Curtis' article, "Civil Service Reform"; gives his opinion on the subject; differs with his opinion on the reelection of President Ulysses S. Grant. ]
  - Carl Schurz to George William Curtis, 1875 Mar 11; ALS, 4 p.
    [Angry that he allowed a cartoon and two column commentary disparaging him as an ultramontane and a mercenary adventurer to be published in
    Harper's Weekly
    feels the article is meant to stir up hostility against him because of his foreign birth; defends his loyalty to America. ]
  - Carl Schurz to George William Curtis, 1875 Oct 20; AL, 1 p. (fragment)
    [Called at
    to discuss public affairs; did not find him; admits to being a bit lame; hopes to hear from him.]
  - Carl Schurz to George William Curtis, 1876 Mar 28; ALS, 1 p.
    [Thanks him for kind letter of sympathy (on death of wife Margarete Schurz) and for his friendship during this difficult time.]
  - Carl Schurz to George William Curtis, 1877 Apr 10; ALS, 1 p.
    [Informs him that Bishop Whipple is held in high esteem in Washington; believes that there are no plans in the Department of the Interior to remove Major Stowe.]
  - Carl Schurz to George William Curtis, 1877 Jul 10; ALS, 1 p.
    [Acknowledges kind note and a pamphlet; informs him that the President [ Rutherford B. Hayes] is well aware of the impact of his actions.]
  - Carl Schurz to George William Curtis, 1878 Jan 12; ALS, 2 p.
    [Has received his letter recommending Mr. Fiske for the Pension Agency in New York; has had 2 interviews with him; agrees with President [Rutherford B.] Hayes that Pension Agents should have an honorable Army record; informs him that the President would like to discuss ideas with him on next visit to Washington. ]
  - Carl Schurz to George William Curtis, 1879 Dec 9; ALS, 4 p.
    [Disagrees with him on the Indian question; believes it is unlikely that Congress will transfer control of the Indian Service; doubts [Ulysses S.] Grant will be re-elected; comments on opposition to Grant in Republican ranks; mentions that the "scratchers" of New York oppose Grant and that he cannot win the state without their aid.]
  - Carl Schurz to George William Curtis, 1883 Feb 5; ALS, 2 p.
    [Wants to know if he accepted an article (by another writer) that he forwarded; asks if he wrote
    article on Fitz-John Porter. ]
  - Carl Schurz to George William Curtis, 1885 Jul 18; ALS, 3 p.
    [Acknowledges receipt of his letter; believes it contains a thought-provoking proposition; claims that commitments preclude a meeting on short notice; needs time to reply to issues; discusses a letter by Moses Williams to [Philander] Deming asking Schurz to give his opinion on methods to strengthen President [Grover] Cleveland against the anti-reform element in his own party.]
  - Carl Schurz to H[jalmar] H[jorth] Boyesen, 1886 Apr 12; ALS, 2 p.
    [Recalls their first meeting at Putnam's; would welcome seeing him again and discuss the Dr. Kinkel library.]
  - Carl Schurz to George William Curtis, 1887 Jun 23; ALS, 7 p.
    [Thanks for the kind judgment on his book and for discussing it in his editorial columns; seeks advice on suggested political and military history of the Civil War; questions the feasibility of writing such a work on evidentiary grounds and on the brief time since the end of the war; expresses interest in doing the project; discusses a project to write the history of the new German Empire; would rather not live abroad to do research; describes his work on his recollections.]
  - Carl Schurz to George William Curtis, 1887 Jul 7; ALS, 4 p.
    [Considers a suggestion to write a civil rather than military history of the Civil War; does not mind that this project will absorb all his time; believes that the appointment of Potts endangers the position of [John] Jay and Richmond; comments on his health, especially his ability to walk with only one stick.]
  - Carl Schurz to George William Curtis, 1887 Aug 7; ALS, 4 p.
    [Agrees with the critical opinions in his political article; disappointed that President [Grover] Cleveland is unwilling to investigate the Higgins-Thomas-Raisin case; feels that the president's actions have alienated many of his former supporters; encloses article from a reform paper that dismayed him.]
  - Carl Schurz to H[jalmar] H[jorth] Boyesen, 1888 Jan 21; ALS, 3 p.
    [Disappointed at the news that
    Evening Post
    will not employ Spielhagen, who was in his Burschenschaft (fraternity) in Bonn; recounts his efforts to get him connected with the New York Staatszeitung; will also write to a German paper in the West on his behalf.]
  - Carl Schurz to George William Curtis, 1888 Apr 5; ALS, 3 p.
    [Hopes to discuss politics with him before sailing for Germany; intends to stay until September unless the Republicans nominate [James G.] Blaine again; would return in time for the campaign; has heard bad things about the Treasury Department in the matter of removals; thanks him for kind words in
    about his own speech on the dead Kaiser.]
  - Carl Schurz to George William Curtis, 1889 Mar 23; ALS, 3 p.
    [Thanks him for copies of his "great Gettysburg oration" and his Washington Monument speech; has written Mr. Wanamaker for an explanation of his financial transactions during the presidential campaign; asks him to intervene because the letter has not been answered.]
  - Carl Schurz to George William Curtis, 1889 May 4; ALS, 3 p.
    [Praises his address which was critical of President [Grover] Cleveland's administration; calls Cleveland an old-fashioned Indiana politician; praises Bishop Potter's "glorious" sermon; disappointed that President Cleveland appointed his own brother to political office.]
  - Carl Schurz to George William Curtis, 1889 May 15; ALS, 2 p.
    [Doubts whether [William D.] Foulke's plan will be profitable; suggests investigating the matter with him.]
  - Carl Schurz to George William Curtis, 1889 Oct 22; ALS, 1 p.
    [Invites him to dinner; informs him that the guests will include Mr. and Mrs. [Grover] Cleveland and Dr. Sievelzing, head of German delegation to maritime conference in Washington. ]
  - Carl Schurz to H[jalmar] H[jorth] Boyesen, 1889 Dec 3; ALS, 1 p.
    [Encloses a letter to Secretary Bayard.]
  - Carl Schurz to George William Curtis, 1890 Feb 23; ALS, 1 p.
    [Invites him to his birthday dinner on March 1.]
  - Carl Schurz to George William Curtis, 1890 Dec 23; ALS, 2 p.
    [Believes that he should draft a letter to the president [Benjamin Harrison] instead of Schurz because of his abilities, knowledge, and position. Informs him about his many commitments, including an article on [Abraham] Lincoln due for the
    Atlantic Monthly
    in early January.]
  - Carl Schurz to George William Curtis, 1890 Dec 25; ALS, 1 p.
    [Reemphasizes that if a letter from Republican civil service reformers is to have any effect on the president [Benjamin Harrison], Curtis should write it.]
  - Carl Schurz to George William Curtis, 1891 Jan 24; ALS, 1 p.
    [Agrees with him and Rogers on "what is now to be done and what is not to be done." Says that Rogers' letter has undermined his opinion of the president; believes the president is afraid of politicians and does not trust reformers. Will return Roosevelt's letter to Rogers.]
  - Carl Schurz to George William Curtis, 1891 Apr 20; ALS, 2 p.
    [Declines an invitation to the Thomas dinner because of prior commitment.]
  - Carl Schurz to George William Curtis, 1891 Jul 7; ALS, 2 p.
    [Appreciates his kind words about his Lincoln paper; praises his essay on Holmes in
    expects to be in Buffalo at the meeting of the National League. ]
  - Carl Schurz to George William Curtis, 1892 Mar 1; ALS, 2 p.
    [Sends him a draft which, in his opinion, is "stupid." Asks him to look at it critically and do with it whatever is necessary. Mentions letter from Storey reporting on plans for mass meeting in favor of [Grover] Cleveland in Boston; informs him that Cleveland said that he is not withdrawing from the contest.]
  - Carl Schurz to George William Curtis, 1892 Mar 12; ALS, 2 p.
    [Discussed the "Circular" with Storey; suggests change of certain words and phrases; is confident that Curtis will give the document its final shape.]
  - Carl Schurz to George William Curtis, 1893 Mar 1; ALS, 1 p.
    [Invites him to dinner party where he will meet Joseph Jefferson, the actor.]
- Miscellaneous
  - Questionnaire of the National Almanac, completed and signed by Carl Schurz, 1862 Oct 18; Questionnaire
    [with printed note from George W. Childs requesting information for the
    National Almanac
    . ]